Pegi Deitz Shea Papers 1997.0068
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Pegi Deitz Shea Papers
undated, 1989-2007.
1997.0068
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
8.85 Linear feet
Pegi Deitz Shea was born 22 September 1960, in Matawan, NJ, the daughter of George A. Deitz (a high school teacher and coach) and Margaret J. (a legal secretary) Devlin. She attended Rutgers College, Rutgers University (1982) and has been awarded the Evelyn Hamilton Award for Creative Writing, Rutgers College (1982).
Shea, Pegi Deitz.
Biography
Pegi Deitz Shea was born 22 September 1960, in Matawan, NJ, the daughter of George A. Deitz and Margaret J. Devlin. She attended Rutgers College, Rutgers University (1982) and has been awarded the Evelyn Hamilton Award for Creative Writing, Rutgers College (1982). Ms. Shea is a member of St. Bernard's Christian Service Committee, Society of Children's Book Writers and Illustrators ( New England SCBWI Conference Planning Committee member, 1992-1993). Ms. Shea is the president of Pegi Deitz Shea Public Relations in addition to being a freelance writer, poet and children's book author.
Scope and Content
The collection includes materials associated with the author's books. Materials for Bungalow, Fungalow (CLC C1190) and The Whispering Cloth, originally titled “Stitches”, includes correspondence, research materials, photographs, manuscripts and galleys of the books, in addition to clippings, presentation and marketing materials.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of children's literature. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Children's Writer [magazine], 9:12, 11:8, 13:5, 13:6, 13:8, 13:9, 14:2, 14:3, 14:7, 14:9, July, 2000-April 2005..
Footsteps: African American History [magazine], 2:3, 3:1, May/June 2000, Jan./Feb. 2001.
Institute of Children's Literature, 2005 Book Markets for Children's Writers, Institute of Children's Literature, 2004.
Institute of Children's Literature, 2005 Magazine Markets for Children's Writers, Institute of Children's Literature, 2004.
Institute of Children's Literature, The Children's Writer Guide, 1998, Institute of Children's Literature, c. 1996. Dodd Call No. CLC A1263.
Ladybug [magazine], Feb. 2000.
NERA Journal, 40:1, 2004.
Shea, Pegi Deitz, The Whispering Cloth, Caroline House, Boyds Mills Press, 1995. Dodd Call No. CLC D472.
Tierney, Susan M., ed., Children's Writer Guide to 2004, The Writer's Bookstore, 2004.
Tierney, Susan M., ed., Children's Writer Guide to 2005, The Writer's Bookstore, 2005.
UMag, #36, Spring 2005.
4 photographs of Ruth and Samaria Bestman
3 3 1/2 inch diskettes, Word 1995 format, Tangled Threads, Sept. 2002.
Bibliography
Children's Books by Pegi Deitz Shea
Bungalow Fungalow, Clarion, 1991.
The Whispering Cloth, Boyds Mills, 1995.
New Moon, Boyd Mills Press, 1996.
Ekaterina Gordeva, Chelsea House Publications, 1998.
The Impeachment Process (Your Government: How It Works), Chelsea House Publications, 2000.
I See Me, HarperFestival, 2000.
The Carpet Boy's Gift, Tilbury House, 2003.
Tangled Threads: A Hmong Girl's Story, Clarion, 2003.
Ten Mice for Tet, Chronicle Books, 2003.
Liberty Rising: The Story of the Statue of Liberty, Henry Holt and Company, 2005.
Children's Stories and Articles by Pegi Deitz Shea
"Canning Day." Accepted by Highlights for Children.
"Dirty Little Snake," Ladybug, Feb. 2000.
"A Family Torn Apart by War," Footsteps: African American History, 3:1 Jan-Feb. 2001.
"High School: Get over It!" (unpublished?)
Adult Articles by Pegi Deitz Shea
"Adolescent Non-Fiction Books: Beyond Bios and History," forthcoming.
"Clips and How to Get Them," Children's Writer 14:7, Reb. 2005: 6-7.
"En Route to Non-Fiction Picture Book Sales," Children's Writer 13:9, April 2004: 1-3.
"Help Us Help Them: 'Support' Publications Aid Children and Families," 2005 Magazine Markets for Children, 2004: 35-38.
"How to Form a Critique Group," Children's Writer 9:12, July 2002: 11.
"Huge Market for Sports Articles" Children's Writer 14:3, Oct. 2004: 1, 4-5.
"Like Water for Poetry," Children's Writer 14:9, April 2005: 1-3.
"My Writing Process: A Repeating Number," NERA Journal 40:1, 2004: 26-30.
"Never Underestimate the Value of Grandparents" (also called "The Grandest Love"), The Hartford Courant, 11 Sept. 1998.
"Photography in Picture Books: A Snappy Approach," Children's Writer 14:2, Sept. 2004: 1-3.
"Sports and Recreation Writing from a Jock's Point of View," Children's Writer 13:12, July 2004: 6-7.
"Teens: Coping with Life's Issues," 2005 Book Markets for Children's Writers, 2004: 63-76.
"The Truth is in the Deals," forthcoming,.
"What a Good Time for Novelists!", Children's Writer 13:8, March 2004: 1-3.
"Poetic Ideas In and Out of Context: A Poetry Writing Workshop," Children's Writer Guide to 2004, 2004: 219-24.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Ms. Shea in 1999. Ms. Shea has donated materials for later books yearly from 2000-2005.
American poetry.; Artwork.; Author.; Books.; Children's literature—Connecticut authors.; Children's poetry, American.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts.; Northeast Children's Literature Collection.; Photographs.; Poet.; Press releases.; Publications.
- Series I: Publications, undated, 1989-2005
  - "Adolescent Non-Fiction Books: Beyond Bios and History" [article], undated
    - Typescript, undated (Box 5:, Folder 45)
  - Bungalow, Fungalow, 1991
    - Contract, 1990 (Box 3:, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript, 1989-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Galleys (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Production proof (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Book Catalogue, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Presentation evaluations, 1994 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Presentation Photographs, 1994 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Children's work, 1991 (Box 3:, Folder 9)
    - Signings and Publicity, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - "Canning Day" [short story], undated
    - Correspondence, 1993 January - 2000 August (Box 5:, Folder 46)
    - Notes, undated (Box 5:, Folder 47)
    - "On Canning Day" [typescript], 1992 September 11 (Box 5:, Folder 48)
    - Typescripts, 1992 September 19 (Box 5:, Folder 49)
    - Typescripts, 1992 October 12 (Box 5:, Folder 50)
    - Typescripts, 1993 June (Box 5:, Folder 51)
    - Typescripts, 1994 January 20 (Box 5:, Folder 52)
    - Typescript, 1994 January 26 (Box 5:, Folder 53)
    - Typescript, 1994 July 24 (Box 5:, Folder 54)
    - Typescript, 1995 April 22 (Box 5:, Folder 55)
    - Undated typescripts (Box 5:, Folder 56)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 5:, Folder 57)
  - The Carpet Boy's Gift, 2003
    - Dummy by Leane Morin [copy], undated (Box 3:, Folder 36)
    - Tilbury House catalog, 2003 (Box 5:, Folder 58)
  - "Clips and How to Get Them" [article]
    - Photocopy of article, 2005 February (Box 5:, Folder 59)
  - "The Descriptive Zone: Beyond Adjectives and Adverbs" [presentation]
    - Typescript, ca. 2000 October (Box 5:, Folder 60)
    - Fliers, 2000 October (Box 5:, Folder 61)
  - "The Dirty Little Snake" [short story], 2000
    - Correspondence, 1996 February - 2000 February (Box 5:, Folder 62)
    - Typescript, 1996 February 27 (Box 5:, Folder 63)
    - Typescripts, 12 March 1996 (Box 5:, Folder 64)
    - Typescripts, undated (Box 5:, Folder 65)
    - Contract, 21 August 1998 (Box 5:, Folder 66)
    - Photocopy of story, 2000 February (Box 5:, Folder 67)
    - First galleys [photocopy], 1998 July 28 (Box 3:, Folder 37)
  - "En Route to Non-Fiction Picture Book Sales" [article], 2004
    - Correspondence, 2003 October (Box 5:, Folder 68)
    - Research and notes, ca. 2003 October (Box 5:, Folder 69)
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 April (Box 5:, Folder 70)
  - "A Family Torn Apart by War" [article], 2001
    - Correspondence, 2000 January - October (Box 5:, Folder 71)
    - Outline for Footsteps Liberia issue, undated (Box 5:, Folder 72)
    - Notes, undated (Box 5:, Folder 73)
    - Research clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 5:, Folder 74)
    - First draft [manuscript], 2000 May 23 (Box 5:, Folder 75)
    - Second draft [typescript], 2000 May 27 (Box 5:, Folder 76)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 5:, Folder 77)
    - Children's poetry, 2000 (Box 5:, Folder 78)
    - Photocopy of article, 2001 January - February (Box 5:, Folder 79)
  - "The Grandest Love" [essay], 1998
    General note
    Published as "Never Underestimate the Value of Grandparents"
    - Typescript, undated (Box 5:, Folder 80)
  - “Helping” (?)
    - Children's work, undated (Box 3:, Folder 35)
  - "High School: Get over It!" [essay], undated
    - Typescript, undated (Box 5:, Folder 81)
  - "How to Form a Critique Group" [article], 2002
    - Photocopy of article, 2000 July (Box 5:, Folder 82)
  - "Huge Market for Sports Articles" [article], 2004
    - Correspondence, 2004 July (Box 5:, Folder 83)
    - Research and notes, ca. 2004 July (Box 5:, Folder 84)
    - Draft [typescript], undated (Box 5:, Folder 85)
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 October (Box 5:, Folder 86)
  - I See Me, 2000
    - Photocopies of illustrations, 1999 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 38)
    - Galleys [photocopies], 1998 August 31 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1992 January - 2000 November (Box 6:, Folder 87)
    - Typescripts, 1997 October - 1998 April (Box 6:, Folder 88)
    - Related manuscripts, ca. 1998 (Box 6:, Folder 89)
    - Book signing flyers, undated (Box 6:, Folder 90)
    - Book review, 2000 November 17 (Box 6:, Folder 91)
    - Royalty statements, 2000 (Box 6:, Folder 92)
    - Clippings, undated (Box 6:, Folder 93)
  - The Impeachment Process, 2000
    - Background and Notes, undated, 1999 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 31)
    - Quotes and Sources, undated, 1999 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 32)
    - Final Draft, 1999 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence, 1999 May - July (Box 6:, Folder 94)
    - "Your Government: How it Works" series information, ca. 1999 (Box 6:, Folder 95)
    - Outline, 1999 July (Box 6:, Folder 96)
    - First complete draft, 1999 July 13 (Box 6:, Folder 97)
    - "About the Author,", ca. 1999 (Box 6:, Folder 98)
    - Contract, 1999 April 26 (Box 6:, Folder 99)
    - Bill for service, 1999 August 4 (Box 6:, Folder 100)
  - "Like Water for Poetry" [article], 2005
    - Correspondence, 2004 December - 2005 January (Box 6:, Folder 101)
    - Research and notes, 2004 December - 2005 January (Box 6:, Folder 102)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 6:, Folder 103)
    - Photocopy of article, 2005 April (Box 6:, Folder 104)
  - "Marc's Fairway", undated
    - Correspondence, 1998 February - 1999 November (Box 6:, Folder 105)
    - Typescript, 1997 February 18 (Box 6:, Folder 106)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 6:, Folder 107)
    - Partial galleys [photocopy], ca. 1999 April (Box 6:, Folder 108)
    - Clippings, 1997 June 8 (Box 6:, Folder 109)
  - "My Writing Process: A Repeating Number" [article], 2004
    - First draft and photocopy, 2003 December 10 (Box 6:, Folder 110)
    - Second draft [typescript], 2004 February 24 (Box 6:, Folder 111)
    - Third draft [typescript], undated (Box 6:, Folder 112)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 6:, Folder 113)
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 114)
  - “New Moon”
    - Children's work, undated (Box 4:, Folder 30)
  - Newspaper publications, 1987 May - 2003 August (Box 6:, Folder 115)
  - Personal correspondence, 1999 June - 2001 March (Box 6:, Folder 116)
  - "Photography in Picture Books: A Snappy Approach" [article], 2004
    - Correspondence, 2004 June (Box 6:, Folder 117)
    - Typescript, 2004 June 17 (Box 6:, Folder 118)
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 September (Box 6:, Folder 119)
  - Root, undated
    - Foreword / afterword [typescript], undated (Box 6:, Folder 120)
  - "Sports and Recreation Writing from a Jock's Point of View" [article], 2004
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 July (Box 6:, Folder 121)
  - Tangled Threads: A Hmong Girl's Story, 2003
    - Annotated typescript [large copy], undated (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 40)
    - Galleys (author's set), 2003 February 27 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 41)
    - Galleys [photocopy], 2003 February (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 42)
    - Jacket proof, 2003 (Box 3 [OS]:, Folder 43)
    - Correspondence, 1997 April - 2004 January (Box 6:, Folder 122)
    - Early chapters with readers' comments [folder 1 of 5], 1996 (Box 6:, Folder 123)
    - Early chapters with readers' comments [folder 2 of 5], 1996 (Box 6:, Folder 124)
      Laura Williams's comments.
    - Early chapters with readers' comments [folder 3 of 5], 1996 (Box 6:, Folder 125)
    - Early chapters with readers' comments [folder 4 of 5], 1996 (Box 6:, Folder 126)
      Lance Sidney's comments.
    - Early chapters with readers' comments [folder 5 of 5], 1996 (Box 6:, Folder 127)
    - Second draft [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 1996 (Box 7:, Folder 128)
    - Second draft [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 1996 (Box 7:, Folder 129)
    - Third draft with revision notes [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 1997 (Box 7:, Folder 130)
    - Third draft with revision notes [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 1997 (Box 7:, Folder 131)
    - Draft [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 1997 September 1 (Box 7:, Folder 132)
    - Draft [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 1997 September 1 (Box 7:, Folder 133)
    - Revision [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 1998 June - July (Box 7:, Folder 134)
    - Revision [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 1998 June - July (Box 7:, Folder 135)
    - Partial draft [typescript], 2004 September 14 (Box 8:, Folder 136)
    - Fifth draft [typescript], 2001 (Box 8:, Folder 137)
    - Sixth draft [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 2001 August (Box 8:, Folder 138)
    - Sixth draft [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 2001 August (Box 8:, Folder 139)
    - Sixth draft [typescript copy, folder 1 of 2], 2001 August (Box 8:, Folder 140)
    - Sixth draft [typescript copy, folder 2 of 2], 2001 August (Box 8:, Folder 141)
    - Copy-edited typescript [folder 1 of 2], 2002 June (Box 8:, Folder 142)
    - Copy-edited typescript [folder 2 of 2], 2002 June (Box 8:, Folder 143)
    - Final draft [typescript, folder 1 of 2], 2002 August (Box 8:, Folder 144)
    - Final draft [typescript, folder 2 of 2], 2002 August (Box 9:, Folder 145)
    - Revised typescript [folder 1 of 2], 2003 January 13 (Box 9:, Folder 146)
    - Revised typescript [folder 2 of 2], 2003 january 13 (Box 9:, Folder 147)
    - Undated draft A [typescript, folder 1 of 2] (Box 9:, Folder 148)
    - Undated draft A [typescript, folder 2 of 2] (Box 9:, Folder 149)
    - Undated draft B [typescript, folder 1 of 2] (Box 9:, Folder 150)
    - Undated draft B [typescript, folder 2 of 2] (Box 9:, Folder 151)
    - Uncorrected proof, 2003 (Box 9:, Folder 152)
    - Clippings, 2003-2004 (Box 9:, Folder 153)
  - "Teens: Coping with Life's Issues" [article], 2004
    - Correspondence, 2004 April - June (Box 10:, Folder 154)
    - Notes and research, ca. 2004 May (Box 10:, Folder 155)
    - Typescript, 2004 May 13 (Box 10:, Folder 156)
  - Ten Mice for Tet, 2003
    - Galleys [photocopy], 2002 june 12 (Box 3:, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence, 2000 August - December (Box 10:, Folder 157)
    - Correspondence, 2001 February - May (Box 10:, Folder 158)
    - Correspondence, 2001 June - August (Box 10:, Folder 159)
    - Correspondence, 2001 September - October (Box 10:, Folder 160)
    - Correspondence, 2001 November - 2002 March (Box 10:, Folder 161)
    - Correspondence, 2002 April - August (Box 10:, Folder 162)
    - Undated correspondence (Box 10:, Folder 163)
    - Illustration suggestions, 2001 September 11 (Box 10:, Folder 164)
    - Contract, 2001 October 2 (Box 10:, Folder 165)
    - Review, 2003 December 16 (Box 10:, Folder 166)
  - "The Truth is in the Deals" [article], undated
    - Submission print-out, 2004 September 9 (Box 10:, Folder 167)
  - "What a Good Time for Novelists!" [article], 2004
    - Photocopy of article, 2004 March (Box 10:, Folder 168)
  - The Whispering Cloth, 1995
    - Contract, 1992 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Original Manuscript, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Original Manuscript of Translations, undated (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - First Galleys, undated (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Production proof, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Awards, reviews and clippings, 1994-1995, 2000 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Children's work, 2000 (Box 3:, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence—Children, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence—Children, 2000 (Box 4:, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence—Congratulations, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
    - Marketing materials, undated, 1994-1996 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Photographs—Research, 1993 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - Photographs—Research, 1994 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Presentation evaluations, 1995 (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Research—Hmong Information, 1991-1996 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - Writings about Shea, 2004 January - February (Box 10:, Folder 169)
- 2011 Addition, 1986-2008; Series II
  - 1987-2005 (Box 2011-0038_1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Correspondence, postcards, notes, administrative records, financial records, fliers, books, publications, clippings, photographs, manuscript material [Subjects include: Society of Children’s Book Writers and Illustrators, Dwyers and O’Grady, Agency correspondence & some rejects, Jennifer Flannery, Kouts correspondence, "Liberty Rising," Children’s Writer Guide to 2008, Dr. Launch 1986-1987.]
  - 2000-2007 (Box 2008_0058_1)
    Books, correspondence, illustrations, manuscripts, notes, photographs, publications [Subjects include: American poetry, children's literature, Connecticut authors, young adult literature.]